<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-25T06:31:41+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The state of RMagick development]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/07/25/the-state-of-rmagick-development/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-25T04:40:18+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/07/25/the-state-of-rmagick-development</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday <a href="https://github.com/rmagick/rmagick/issues/18#issuecomment-50022523">someone got fed up</a> with the situation that the RMagick gem is in and forked the project.</p>

<p>Neither <a href="https://github.com/rmagick/rmagick/network">is this the first time</a>, nor do I know if this fork will help the project at large, but I think it&rsquo;s time people got to know what&rsquo;s going on with the project.</p>

<p>All of which I&rsquo;m going to write might be obvious, old news or stuff people already knew in one way or another, but here it is anyway.
Here&rsquo;s some backstory that might answer the following question:</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;What&rsquo;s going on with RMagick?&rdquo;</em></p>

<p>Or rather&hellip;</p>

<p><em>&ldquo;Why is <strong>nothing</strong> happening with RMagick?&rdquo;</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving from Squarespace to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/07/20/moving-from-squarespace-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-20T13:51:13+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/07/20/moving-from-squarespace-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Squarespace had been my blogging platform of choice for numerous years.
It looked good, had good editing features and took care of a lot of stuff for you.
However, when my posting slowed down,
I started considering whether what I was using was worth the annual bill I was paying.</p>

<p>I needed something that was both cheaper and that gave me a bit more control.
I was recommended Octopress by a colleague and decided to give it a spin;
I realized very quickly that this platform was a much better fit for me.</p>

<p>These are some thoughts I&rsquo;ve gathered up on the subject, about a month after moving.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Currying and other Haskell spices]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/01/21/currying-and-other-haskell-spices/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-21T23:24:04+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2014/01/21/currying-and-other-haskell-spices</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most people who start looking at Haskell come from a background of one of the
more established languages. Be it Java, Ruby, Python or something else; most
often in those method signatures very clearly define the way in which the
methods can be called.</p>

<p>Not only does Haskell do things a bit differently, the differences allow for
increased flexibility when it comes to usage of functions in general.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim search and replace in bulk]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/16/vim-search-and-replace-in-bulk/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T13:57:07+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/16/vim-search-and-replace-in-bulk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a while you&rsquo;ll have some word or phrase that is present in
multiple files across your project. Finding all of instances can be done with
tools like <code>grep</code> outside of Vim. You could probably also use <code>sed</code>, <code>awk</code> or
some other tool to perform a substitution inside these files.</p>

<p>While there&rsquo;s nothing wrong with this approach, what if you wanted to do this
kind of multi-file search and replace inside Vim?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Adult gaming]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/adult-gaming/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-12T13:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/12/adult-gaming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Based on an rather small amount of unscientifically acquired data, a handful of
anecdotes and a healthy dose of prejudice, I&rsquo;m going to make the following
statement:</p>

<p><strong>Large parts of the previous generations are incompatible with video games.</strong></p>

<p>This isn&rsquo;t a new revelation. It&rsquo;s not some recent discovery, nor is it
something I think there will be much of a debate about. It&rsquo;s just me venting.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Planescape: Torment could have been more]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/09/planescape-torment-could-have-been-more/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-09T13:00:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/09/planescape-torment-could-have-been-more</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In contrast to Fallout 2, which I finished in my early teens, I got around to
playing through <em>Planescape: Torment</em> about half a year ago. Just as everyone
around the net had said, it was a world to get lost in, with interesting
characters, ample amounts of dialogue and a captivating setting that let the
imagination flow.</p>

<p>While I could talk at length about the many things that make this game so
remarkable, others have already done this many times over; &ldquo;Final frontier&rdquo;
wrote <a href="https://medium.com/final-frontier/35ffb4e847cc">a good blog post on the subject</a> about a month ago, well worth
reading.</p>

<p>Instead, I&rsquo;d like to talk about what I felt was missing in this beautiful game.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Screencasts in Linux]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/08/screencasts-in-linux/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-08T16:42:54+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/08/screencasts-in-linux</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Some time ago I wrote a rant about the
<a href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/03/15/when-the-tools-just-dont-work/">sorry state of streaming on Linux</a>. About a month ago I needed to
find an application which would record my desktop for a screencast, giving me
a perfect opportunity to see if the situation had changed somewhat in this
field.</p>

<p>While streaming is still quite bad (video+audio works but there&rsquo;s still nothing
like <a href="http://obsproject.com/">OBS</a>), desktop recording is in a better spot
since you only need the raw footage (bells and whistles can be handled
afterwards in a video editor). Although it took some searching, I actually
found something with which I can reliably record my desktop, with microphone
audio.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Old favourites]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/07/old-favourites/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-07T15:36:57+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/09/07/old-favourites</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>At times I forget why I loved a certain artist or composition. The same happens
with books, video games and movies. Time has passed and having indulged in the
work of art so many times made me forget what made it so special in the first
place.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Anime is still anime]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/06/29/anime-is-still-anime/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-29T16:33:04+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/06/29/anime-is-still-anime</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Recently my co-worker recommended me an anime series called &ldquo;Attack on Titan&rdquo;.
The clips on Youtube looked good; the style was pretty cool, it looked like an
interesting setting and it looked like the focus was on people trying to
survive in a tough world.</p>

<p>Having seen all of the currently released episodes, I can say that all of the
above is true! The style, the setting, the story; all of that is there and is
enjoyable.</p>

<p>The big issue with the series is that all of above mentioned qualities are
wrapped in the shitty package of being an anime.</p>

<p>Spoilers ahead.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Macros and the expression register in Vim]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/05/28/macros-and-the-expression-register-in-vim/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-28T18:30:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/05/28/macros-and-the-expression-register-in-vim</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Macros and expressions are two tools that serve the purpose of saving you from
either repeating a tedious process or the time switching back and forth between
shells to run scripts to manipulate your data with. Both can be (and often are)
used separately, but can be used in tandem to do some pretty cool stuff.</p>

<p>So let&rsquo;s introduce them and see how they work.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim plugins - Why, How and Which]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/04/13/vim-plugins-why/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-13T23:12:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/04/13/vim-plugins-why</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of times when I meet &ldquo;Vim neophytes&rdquo; they mention that Vim is a great
editor, but they miss certain features that they find in their previous
editor/IDE of choice. Often this will be a case of them not having learnt the
Vim way of doing the same task, but occasionally you&rsquo;ll have to tell them that
&ldquo;Vim doesn&rsquo;t do that&rdquo;.<br/>
Indeed, these days if you don&rsquo;t want to hop between different applications (all
of them having the primary purpose of editing text of some kind) you&rsquo;ll want
features that go beyond &ldquo;editing text&rdquo;.</p>

<h4>These days an editor can&rsquo;t just be an editor.</h4>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not ready for the switch]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/05/10/not-ready-for-the-switch/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T14:12:25+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/05/10/not-ready-for-the-switch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, for some unknown reason, <a href="http://5digits.org/pentadactyl/">Pentadactyl</a> decided that it didn&rsquo;t want to work any more.
I still have no idea why, and since I&rsquo;ve been suspending my computer for quite
a few days now, it might actually have to do with me upgrading Firefox from 11
to 12 quite recently. The problem was actually pretty easily solved by
downloading the latest nightly and just fire that up, but before I did that, the
sudden loss of Vim-style navigation inspired me to pick up an old project of
mine:</p>

<p>Moving from Firefox to uzbl.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When the tools just don't work]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/03/15/when-the-tools-just-dont-work/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T12:38:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/03/15/when-the-tools-just-dont-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a while you stumble on that area of software that Linux just
doesn&rsquo;t have covered. You might now be thinking that I&rsquo;d like to talk about
audio and video editing. A fair guess, since you&rsquo;ll hear people talk about
these two as areas where the other platforms have significantly more
sophisticated software available. But this isn&rsquo;t what I&rsquo;m going to talk about.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code I enjoy]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/02/27/code-i-enjoy/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-27T18:59:41+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/02/27/code-i-enjoy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a CS student means that I will be forced to code in a variety of
languages. A lot of our code will be written in Java or C++, but we&rsquo;ll
necessarily get in touch with many other languages, spanning over multiple
paradigms.</p>

<p>By no means am I a good programmer yet, but the exposure to the different ways
of crafting code has led me to think about what I value (as a novice
programmer) in a language. It&rsquo;s, after all, my main tool of expression.<br/>
Is it the brevity of the code? What the community surrounding the language is
like? Paradigm or strong vs. weak typing? Or could it be that I need the
language to be as “simple” as possible for me to be able to formulate ideas?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Att stå still gåendes]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/01/26/att-sta-still-gaendes/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-26T00:36:52+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/01/26/att-sta-still-gaendes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>En ny vecka gryr och jag står med hopp.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just a toy]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/08/17/just-a-toy/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-17T17:14:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/08/17/just-a-toy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I had an experience that was moving. It felt special, yet to the
casual observer it would have been anything but special.</p>

<p>It involved a <a href="http://www.puzl.co.uk/product_thumb.php?img=images/mini2_3_500.jpg&amp;w=400&amp;h=400">Rubik puzzle</a>
that I hadn’t solved yet, and I just felt like finishing it. After all, I know
how to solve a 2x2x2, so this one shouldn&rsquo;t have posed a problem.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laughs from nowhere]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/05/25/laughs-from-nowhere/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-25T12:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/05/25/laughs-from-nowhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humour is a force that binds and divides.</p>

<p>It is as hard to define as the force of love and yet as simple. When you burst
out into an honest laughter, just as with love, it just happens.<br/>
Similarly, what may be infatuating for one, might be repulsive to the other.
I expect everyone to have wondered why person next to them is laughing, just as
I expect most people to have encountered love they cannot understand.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unreal Tournament vs. Quake]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/01/12/unreal-tournament-vs-quake/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-12T18:54:49+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/01/12/unreal-tournament-vs-quake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Within the genre of first person shooters there is a sub-genre that are often
called arena shooters.</p>

<p>Arena shooters focus on dropping you and a bunch of opponents into enclosed
arenas with a bunch weapons with the sole objective of making your opponents
less intact than you are. With such a simple premise, the creators of such
games are forced to make the basics right, the core shooting and the movement
in the world. The expectations on the breadth of the game are lowered in favor
of a perfect &ldquo;feel&rdquo;. Only when the very basics are perfect, the creators start
thinking about adding new gameplay elements on top of the foundation.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The black sheep of social media]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/09/28/the-black-sheep-of-social-media/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-28T00:16:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/09/28/the-black-sheep-of-social-media</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week the company had a group activity where the following question had to
be answered:</p>

<h4>&ldquo;How can we make our company seen?&rdquo;</h4>

<p>A broad but familiar question, one that I assume most companies try to figure
out the answer to.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[At the snap of your fingers]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/20/at-the-snap-of-your-fingers/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-20T18:23:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/20/at-the-snap-of-your-fingers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m by now profoundly tired of the misconception that has been floating around
in our modern digitalized society for too long of a time. It thrives within the
older generations, but is in no way limited to them. It goes like this:</p>

<h4>Piracy is theft!</h4>

<p>Stop. <strong>Now</strong>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
