<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: gaming | Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/categories/gaming/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T17:26:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unreal Tournament vs. Quake]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/01/12/unreal-tournament-vs-quake/"/>
    <updated>2010-01-12T18:54:49+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/01/12/unreal-tournament-vs-quake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Within the genre of first person shooters there is a sub-genre that are often
called arena shooters.</p>

<p>Arena shooters focus on dropping you and a bunch of opponents into enclosed
arenas with a bunch weapons with the sole objective of making your opponents
less intact than you are. With such a simple premise, the creators of such
games are forced to make the basics right, the core shooting and the movement
in the world. The expectations on the breadth of the game are lowered in favor
of a perfect &ldquo;feel&rdquo;. Only when the very basics are perfect, the creators start
thinking about adding new gameplay elements on top of the foundation.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>The two contenders</h2>

<p>When speaking of arena shooters, there are two series that to me stand way
above everything else, and they are both featured in the title of the article.</p>

<p><strong>Quake</strong> was the game that started it all, a masterpiece from id Software that
defined the genre. It&rsquo;s strengths lie in a very clear cut arsenal of weaponry
where close to no overlapping exists, and a very fast unforgiving gameplay.
While there are four iterations of the series, the most prominent and well
respected is Quake III Arena, which for many is the epitome of FPS gaming.</p>

<p><strong>Unreal Tournament</strong> didn&rsquo;t start a genre, but instead showed what should be
expected of it. Not only did it rival Q3 on the basis of incredible core
gameplay (that didn&rsquo;t feel like a simple imitation), it offered more game
modes, better maps and more customizability with the inception of mutators. Add
to that an outstanding amount of official content that was/is continually
expanded, and you&rsquo;ve got something that ends up being &ldquo;Bigger, Better and more
Badass&rdquo; (to quote a certain Epic Games employee).<br/>
Unreal Tournament has by now had four iterations, with UT2003 not being much
more than a solid precursor to UT2004, cutting down the real number to three.
There are important differences between the iterations of Unreal Tournament,
but since the the purpose of the article is comparing what I believe to be the
foremost of both series, UT2004 will be seen as the representative game. While
I don&rsquo;t feel it is fair to disqualify the other two without a proper
explanation, I&rsquo;ll leave that to a different article (some of it has been
covered in my <a href="/blog/2009/06/03/unreal-tournament-3-plus-titan-pack/">UT3 review</a>).</p>

<h2>Basics compared</h2>

<p>The movement is what splits these games apart. Not that the weapons don&rsquo;t have a contributing factor in differentiating the two, but the movement in the two restricts the designs of the maps in a very tangible way, so therefore it will be dealt with first.</p>

<h3>Movement</h3>

<p>Quake 3 with it&rsquo;s strafejumping and rocketjumping will take a player long
distances over a short time, both horizontally and vertically. This forces maps
into accommodating rapid, long distance movement. This has left players with
a history of not more than &ldquo;fairly&rdquo; entertaining maps that are hampered by the
need for simplicity. While this doesn&rsquo;t mean that there are no interesting
maps, they are however quite sparse.<br/>
And yes, I do use &ldquo;interesting&rdquo; and &ldquo;entertaining&rdquo; interchangeably in this case
because I don&rsquo;t find a handful of platforms hanging in space (Longest Yard,
Q3DM17) or two rooms with corridors between them and a cupboard (House of Pain,
Q3DM2) stimulating in any possible way.</p>

<p>Thankfully, with Quake Live the community received a set of maps that are in
general vastly superior to the old maps, but they are still only making the
best out of the situation, following the old guidelines of what can and can&rsquo;t
be done. Expect large swaths of open area, wide corridors and minimal amounts
of vertical obstruction.</p>

<p>If Q3 takes you far in a linear fashion, Unreal Tournament (and especially
2004) takes you a short distance in a more explosive and unpredictable fashion.
Dodging is a shorter movement but happens as suddenly as a rocket jump and the
double jump takes you fairly high without the use of any weapons. This, along
with the absence of the rocket jump is what results in a higher tolerance for
map complexity and &ldquo;right-angle-density&rdquo;. In Quake 3 if a corner comes your
momentum is killed, in Unreal Tournament you&rsquo;re just doing another dodge in
another direction.</p>

<p>The potential for all kinds of wonderful maps is there (as can be seen with
everything from DM-Roughinery to UCMP2-Churn), but it seems that players still
gravitate towards the large maps, where it can take two, three, sometimes even
four full dodge jumps just to get across a corridor, and that&rsquo;s probably not
even a major part of the map (yes DM-Rankin, you&rsquo;re <em>too spacious</em> for 1v1, no
matter how many times you&rsquo;re played in tournaments).</p>

<p>All it really amounts to is that fight, chase and flight is more interesting if
you have to consider multiple angles and directions at all times,
considerations that will never arise in unobstructed environments. Apart from
the effect movement has on map design, I also think that the short range
explosive movement of dodges is more interesting in the heat of battle than
that of rocket jumping.</p>

<h3>Weapons</h3>

<p>So while I would argue for UT2004 having the superior movement system, the same
cannot be said for the weapon arsenal. As mentioned weapons come second after
movement when it comes to importance, but it is not be neglected at all.
There&rsquo;s a reason the saying &ldquo;A shooter is as good as it&rsquo;s weapons&rdquo; exists (as
you might understand, I don&rsquo;t agree with it completely).</p>

<p>Quake 3 has undoubtedly the best arsenal of the two and it might, quite
possibly, have the best one in any FPS. In no way do I mean to belittle the
weapons of Unreal Tournament which are indeed fantastic, but there is simply no
arsenal (that I&rsquo;m aware of) that has so clear roles of application. After one
or two shots fired from every weapon in Q3 you have a perfect understanding of
their usage, and can subsequently start learning how to apply them in combat.
They are few, but they are concise; the Quake 3 arsenal is the
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KISS_principle">KISS</a> principle personified,
covering all ground needed, making no weapon obsolete.</p>

<p>Unreal Tournament 2004 has an arsenal that is more or less double the size,
considering the multiple firing modes offered. The difference here lies in
possibilities offered, and their necessity at all times.</p>

<p>Where Quake 3 stops at the grenade launcher for indirect area denial, UT2004
gives the Assault Rifle grenades for roughly the same result, but also gives
the Flak secondary for instant explosion denial and the Bio carpeting for
delayed but static denial (until the slime explodes).<br/>
Same thing goes for the &ldquo;stream of damage&rdquo; weapons. Q3 has its Lightning Gun,
while UT2004 has two firing modes on the Minigun and the Link Gun shaft. All
three are different, but only slightly. The overlap is noticeable but
fortunately the differences between the weapons and firing modes are pronounced
enough to warrant their inclusion.</p>

<h4>Problems with UT2004</h4>

<p>I have a couple of gripes with the arsenal of UT2004 however that detract from
a game that I otherwise enjoy so much:</p>

<p>First of all, the change from Enforcers to Assault Rifles was a grave mistake
considering how worthless the AR is (even when you dual wield them). Only the
grenades are worth anything, and even then they&rsquo;re fired very slow (if you want
any kind of range with them) and are fairly hard to hit with. Grave mistake.</p>

<p>Secondly, the Link Gun plasma would need to fly as fast as, and have a rate of
fire of, the Plasma Gun to even be remotely useful outside of vehicle and
structure bombardment in Assault/Onslaught.</p>

<p>Finally, I feel that the UT3 versions of the Rocket Launcher and Bio Rifle are
a bit better than the ones of UT2004. RL is easier to get direct hits with (I
don&rsquo;t care much for the grenade functionality) and the Bio Rifle is also easier
to hit with. The fact that the Bio drains instead of insta-kills is also a very
nice feature. These changes are minuscule compared to the other points, but they
still bug me at times.</p>

<h4>The ASMD Shock Rifle</h4>

<p>A matter that will most likely make or break the game for many however is the
Shock Rifle. This is a Swiss army knife of weapons, and I to this day can&rsquo;t
decide if it detracts from or enhances the game. It has a powerful hitscan
attack (45 damage), a spammable secondary (for the same amount of damage), and
not an area denial but powerful <strong>space</strong> denial attack.</p>

<p>The space denial is really the only type of attack that Q3 lacks, however Q3
doesn&rsquo;t need it; the question I ask myself is whether Unreal Tournament needs
it. Space denial is (especially as powerful as the shock combo) the most
versatile tool one can get in an arena shooter according to me, and this
mechanic was and still is a risky business to implement.</p>

<p>Even after so many years of play with it, I can give no straight answer on
whether it is detriment or an benefit to the game.</p>

<h2>Closing thoughts</h2>

<p>UT2004 is most definitely the slower game of the two, but what it looses in
speed it gains in complexity. Rarely have I found matches in Quake that have
provided me with so much joy as the ones I&rsquo;ve had in UT2004, and in the end
I think that&rsquo;s what it&rsquo;s all about.</p>

<p>The thought of comparing UT2004 and Q3 (and to an extent the series) came about
in the midst of an argument during a LAN party, when the choice of game was to
be decided. At the time UT2004 was chosen for it&rsquo;s more enjoyable 1v1 and 2v2
(according to a majority), additional game types and more content in general
helped along the way too.</p>

<p>I respect both games as cornerstones in the FPS realm, but in the end there has
to be one you feel you&rsquo;ll never uninstall.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unreal Tournament 3 + Titan Pack]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/03/unreal-tournament-3-plus-titan-pack/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-03T17:41:28+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/03/unreal-tournament-3-plus-titan-pack</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When Unreal Tournament 3 was officially announced, a wave of mixed feelings
went through the Unreal-community.</p>

<p>UT2004 was essentially everything most people could have ever wanted in terms
of a shooter. Sure, there were going to be UT99 purists who would object to the
style and the zealous Quake gamers who still claim that after Q3 the world
could have stopped spinning, but disregarding people who would never have it
any different than graphically updated clones, UT2004 was a milestone in FPS
gaming. The mechanics were done right, the content was abundant, the community
was sprawling and everything was kept at a impressively high standard. Within
UT2004 we had almost everything we could ask for.</p>

<p>Now I&rsquo;ve only been playing UT3 for the &ldquo;Play UT3 for free!&rdquo;-weekends offered on Steam. Since these have occurred twice I&rsquo;ve got somewhere around 20 hours of total play time. I therefore don&rsquo;t feel entitled to a final opinion, but I want to share my observations.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>A legacy to live up to</h2>

<p>Throughout the history of culture the successful sequels (any field) have made
us relate to the original, yet find new content to explore. Some sequels have
it very easy because the original was of such high quality that the audience
will settle for &ldquo;more of the same&rdquo;, demanding slight tweaks but retaining very
large parts of the structure. Other sequels might have the privilege to work
with a well received but raw original, providing the liberty to shape and/or
expand in many different directions.</p>

<p>UT3 didn&rsquo;t have the luxury of either of those.</p>

<p>The audience had already seen the Unreal Tournament formula go through three
very different, but still coherent and intertwined, iterations. Most content
(and especially the good one) we already had experienced three times over (some
will argue that UT2003 was not as enjoyable as the other two, I respectfully
disagree). This unfortunately put Epic in the situation where anything (that
I can think of) that would stay true to the UT-franchise will inevitably have
been tried, <em>especially</em> after the monstrous amount of content provided with
UT2004. While &ldquo;more of the same&rdquo; didn&rsquo;t necessarily result in a bad game, it
did make a large part of the audience wonder if they were getting their money&rsquo;s
worth, they already had the provided content in older games (and that&rsquo;s
speaking of UT3+TP, vanilla UT3 must have felt like a rip-off).</p>

<p>Unreal Tournament is a franchise that is very flexible when it comes to play
styles, as long as it&rsquo;s futuristic and creatures kill each other it&rsquo;s
acceptable and in canon. The mentioned opportunity of a &ldquo;raw original&rdquo; (which
in this case would mean the mentioned flexibility) is exploited, but it seems
Epic put a lot more pressure on making small changes and execute those well
than taking risks with new styles of play. This is in no way a bad decision,
but it&rsquo;s a stark contrast to what the release of UT2004 looked like. Both fans
and ordinary gamers were treated with (among other things):</p>

<ul>
<li>Close to every game mode ever introduced in UT (including a mind-blowing
reintroduction of Assault)</li>
<li>The inception of the new game modes like Invasion, Mutant and to a lesser
extent Vehicle-CTF (no maps but the support was there).</li>
<li>This deserves it&rsquo;s own point: Onslaught<br/>
Many saw it feasible to detach this as a separate game.</li>
<li>More maps in a UT-release than we had ever seen, each and everyone sticking
to Epic&rsquo;s tradition of being of the best in the industry.</li>
<li>An improved single player that felt interesting enough to keep you
entertained without multiplayer.</li>
</ul>


<p>With this being only some of the big reasons to buy the <em>initial release</em>
(which excludes the fantastic community and official support the game got
post-release) it got hard for UT3 to live up to the expectations.</p>

<h2>The Good and Bad</h2>

<p>First of all, there are two aspects that basically define the feel of playing
a certain shooter. This sole &ldquo;feel&rdquo; can make or break the game. The two aspects
are the movement and the weapons, in no particular order (because should I want
an order I would need another article explaining my choice). All the other
things come secondary.</p>

<h3>The movement</h3>

<p>The movement is essentially a mix between UT2004 and UT99, double jump is there
but you can&rsquo;t add a jump at the end of a dodge. This meant that the verticality
was preserved but some of the horizontality was lost. UT has always been about
the explosive horizontal movement, which is one of the things that made it so
different Quake 3. This statement will make some upset and have them call upon
the different aspects of bunny jumping and RocketLauncher/PlasmaGun maneuvers.
I will however claim that while these are interesting in their own right, the
dodging mechanic found in UT2004 was something sublime that offered the jerky
and unpredictable maneuvers of the Q3-RocketLauncher both inside the heat of
point black combat, and outside when a chase or escape was present.</p>

<p>I will at some point address why I feel UT is superior to Quake, but I think it
is sufficient to say that removing the dodge-jump removed something important.
Some will object saying that UT3 is with it&rsquo;s lack of a dodge-jump similar in
movement to UT99, but this is very far from the truth; UT99 had
a proportionally higher running speed, which made the game feel a lot faster
than UT3.</p>

<p>It takes some time to get used to, but overall it doesn&rsquo;t feel as interesting,
and it&rsquo;s most definitely slower than any of it&rsquo;s predecessors. With that said,
the maps are perfectly aligned with the movement, so it feels right but it&rsquo;s
not what I wanted.</p>

<p>As a minor note I&rsquo;d like to add that they&rsquo;ve added hover boards which are always
available in the Onslaught equivalent called Warfare, this is a nice touch that
remedies some of the camping on vehicle spawns on those huge maps where going
on foot is simply not feasible.</p>

<h3>The weapons</h3>

<p>I will further down address the graphics and art style a bit more thoroughly
but the first thing you notice about the weapons is that they look
unnecessarily contrived. There are more details than you can count, and while
it&rsquo;s never really distracting, a lot of people will prefer the simpler models
shown in previous installments of UT (that might just be nostalgia speaking,
who knows). The feel of the weapons is an improvement however. It seems the
small tweaks added make the weapons feel fresh again, even though we&rsquo;ve had
most of them for four games now (the flak cannon in Unreal was a beast&hellip;).
A quick rundown:</p>

<ul>
<li>Impact hammer has taken the shield gun&rsquo;s place. I understand that some have
gripes with the shield, and I do find this hammer very nice. Sound, visuals
and the power, love them. They didn&rsquo;t however need to make the secondary
attack completely worthless (knocking off powerups with melee anyone?).</li>
<li>The fan favourite Enforcer is back and unfortunately it feels wimpier. This
is sad because the reason people wanted it back was because the UT99
enforcers were monsters, dealing solid damage with good accuracy. This is
better than the Assault Rifle, but it&rsquo;s not the real deal.</li>
<li>The Bio Gun is easier to hit with now, and charged blobs of goo don&rsquo;t make
instant damage, but drains depending on the size of the blob. A welcome
change to one of my favourite weapons.</li>
<li>The Shock Rifle now has harder to hit shock cores, other than that it&rsquo;s the
same thing.</li>
<li>Link Gun is the same deal, although at first, second and third glance it
seemed as Epic had dropped linking. Apparently you have to stand really close
to each other for linking to work. Linking was mainly used in Onslaught so
this change is trivial for me.</li>
<li>The Stinger Minigun is very nice. Sound, visuals and fire modes are all top
notch.</li>
<li>The Flak Cannon seem to fire more shrapnel in a wider spread, and the shells
seem to do more damage. More versatile than ever.</li>
<li>Sniper Rifle&hellip; What can I say? I liked the Lightning Gun, apparently others
didn&rsquo;t.</li>
</ul>


<p>The rest of the weapons are basically the same, nothing special. Overall it&rsquo;s
a mixed bag of changes, but nothing is messed up, and some changes are very
nice so the weapons are fine.</p>

<h3>Gamemodes</h3>

<p>Warfare is basically Onslaught with hoverboards and the ability to capture
nodes instantly with orbs that any player can pick up in their base. An
interesting addition, but nothing special, the games seems to flow the same way
(except on smaller maps when a lot of uncalled for captures occur, IOW love or
hate scenarios). The new vehicles are different but for the most parts nothing
game changing. They are now divided into the Axon (basically the ones found in
UT2004) and the Necris (which are totally different, it&rsquo;s really a question of
trying them out yourself).<br/>
The addition of special events linked to special nodes is a very interesting
twist however.</p>

<p>Deathmatch, Team Deathmatch, Capture the Flag, Vehicle Capture the Flag and
Duel I feel no need to cover because all thing necessary to say have been in
&ldquo;Movement&rdquo;, &ldquo;Weapons&rdquo; or in the short Warfare paragraph.</p>

<p>Then we have Greed (which is nothing but a straight incorporation of the UT2004
mod) and Betrayal, with the latter being such an amazing game mode it has not
only had me thinking about purchasing the game just for this one game mode, it
has also motivated me to start learning UnrealScript so I can port it to
UT2004. It&rsquo;s just that much fun.</p>

<p>Finally there&rsquo;s also a handy new mutator that can really mix up the existing
game modes called the Titan mutator, which can turn any mode into something
completely new. A good addition.</p>

<h3>Graphics and artstyle</h3>

<p>Graphics set to max are nothing but jaw dropping. Period.<br/>
I was also pleased to find that it scaled the graphics on the fly quite nicely,
so what I would expect to lag horribly on my laptop, turned out to run very
well.</p>

<p>The sceneries are rich on details, which at times shifts from being atmospheric
to being cluttered and overloaded. The claim that the characters have an
uncanny resemblance of Gears of War is to a large extent true. Overall I found
the characters to be impressive, but not as interesting as the ones found in
UT2004 were.</p>

<p>The maps are as mentioned well designed, and the artwork here is spot on. Some
of the maps were so beautiful and so amazingly designed it absolutely blew my
mind. Epic are still the ones who provide the best maps in the industry.</p>

<h3>Verdict</h3>

<p>We are treated with unspeakable amounts of FPS games lately, but when it comes
to multiplayer which today is where the games' true lifespan lies, only a few
companies know how to do it right. The Battlefield series is one setting, the
Halo series is another, but in the end it&rsquo;s the futuristic arena combat
introduced by Unreal Tournament and Quake 3 that showed me what real
multiplayer FPS should look like.</p>

<p>UT3 might not be the best game in the series, and it comes in a time where it
is no longer as unique as UT2004 was when it came out, but one needs not to be
outstanding to be good.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
