<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T17:26:59+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Att stå still gåendes]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/01/26/att-sta-still-gaendes/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-26T00:36:52+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/01/26/att-sta-still-gaendes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>En ny vecka gryr och jag står med hopp.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Jobb jag har av varje storlek och slag,<br/>
nog till att fängsla mig natt som dag.</p>

<p>På måndagen är brådska mig främmande.<br/>
Jag lär ej jobba alls, trots att arbetsbördan är skrämmande.</p>

<p>Jag börjar strax, efter lunch, ikväll, inatt.<br/>
Imorgon jobbar jag säkert ifatt.</p>

<p>Tisdag och onsdag far fort likaså,<br/>
jag vet inte ens vad jag skall jobba på.</p>

<p>Vid torsdag morgon är det dags att rappa på,<br/>
halva veckan har gått och resultaten är som bäst små.</p>

<p>Idéerna och visionerna rusar då förbi,<br/>
alla saker som det vore bra om man avklarat i tid.</p>

<p>Men det är ju bara tankar, drömmar som hägrar var dag;<br/>
de ändrar inte något, minst av allt att jag är så svag.</p>

<p>Utan att minnas vad jag gjort, de timmar jag haft allt redo för drift,<br/>
jag sitter där vid midnatt, slagen av min lathet och apatisk som av ett gift.</p>

<p>Natten är dock ej slut för mig, midnatt är blott sen kväll.<br/>
Med småtimmarnas tystnad skall det här väl vara en bagatell?</p>

<p>När fredag dagas är allt för sent och hoppet borta.<br/>
Det enda jag klarade av var att få dagarna att kännas korta.</p>

<p>Skall man ens påbörja dagen när man redan igår var slagen?</p>

<p>Jag kan säkert lura mig själv en dag till,<br/>
“Jag tar igen allt, bara jag vill!”.</p>

<p>Värst är det då jag bara har helgen kvar,<br/>
för det är då tiden som snabbast far.</p>

<p>Flykten från arbete med sig oftast skulden bär,<br/>
men ej på helgen, inte den minsta tyngd på mig tär.</p>

<p>Vet något i mig att ambitioner skall stängas ned? Att lättjan skall skölja över?<br/>
Ohämmad kommer jag göra precis vad jag vill, men ej det jag behöver.</p>

<p>Måndag nalkas och ännu en vecka har försvunnit;<br/>
all den tid man kunde ha använt har mest uti sanden runnit.</p>

<p>Är något annat möjligt?<br/>
Kommer jag att ändras under årets lopp?</p>

<p>Jag kastar bort dessa tankar…</p>

<p>…ty en ny vecka gryr och jag står med hopp.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Just a toy]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/08/17/just-a-toy/"/>
    <updated>2010-08-17T17:14:11+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/08/17/just-a-toy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I had an experience that was moving. It felt special, yet to the
casual observer it would have been anything but special.</p>

<p>It involved a <a href="http://www.puzl.co.uk/product_thumb.php?img=images/mini2_3_500.jpg&amp;w=400&amp;h=400">Rubik puzzle</a>
that I hadn’t solved yet, and I just felt like finishing it. After all, I know
how to solve a 2x2x2, so this one shouldn&rsquo;t have posed a problem.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Handle with care</h2>

<p>Inherent to the puzzle&rsquo;s design was that it turned strangely. In some cases the
turns were smooth, in other it felt like the contraption worked against you.
Regardless of it’s intricacies, I treated and used it like a regular 2x2x2; for
me it was as simple as them both being solved in more or less the same way.</p>

<p>So with the first of three “cubes” solved I started twisting and turning the
second one. As mentioned, it was normal that it occasionally stuck and made
a fuss about simple turns, but I kept on going, a couple of time forcing a turn
through instead of wiggling in the opposite direction.<br/>
After some work however, I had the second cube finished and only the last one
remained. Halfway through the third one however it happened.</p>

<p>Something broke.</p>

<p>Something inside the middle cube went loose, and the entire construction along
with it. This was with me being one and a half algorithm away from finishing the
puzzle for the first time.
I clasped the puzzle, realizing that if I let go of any one loose piece, the
entire thing would fall apart. Greedily, all I thought about was solving it,
despite its fragile state. Holding all the pieces on the first and the middle
cube together took a hand and some pressure, making the cube very hard to
maneuver, but this didn&rsquo;t sway me; there was no giving up. Slowly I approached
the last few moves, and I suddenly hit me that this thing was dying.</p>

<p>It was on respirator and intravenous, and I was still pushing it.</p>

<p>To make things worse, I got to be about four turns away from finishing the
entire puzzle when the thing stuck, there was no moving it. It was as if it had
given up; the last turn was made.
Seeing that there was no way to complete the puzzle, despite being so close,
I gave up. Putting it down on the table it went to pieces, its entire structure
crumbling part by part.</p>

<p>It was a strange moment because it felt like I had witnessed and been part of
a toy&rsquo;s death bed experience.</p>

<p>After looking at the pile of coloured plastic I stepped back and reminded myself
that it was just a toy. I left it at that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Laughs from nowhere]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/05/25/laughs-from-nowhere/"/>
    <updated>2010-05-25T12:18:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2010/05/25/laughs-from-nowhere</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Humour is a force that binds and divides.</p>

<p>It is as hard to define as the force of love and yet as simple. When you burst
out into an honest laughter, just as with love, it just happens.<br/>
Similarly, what may be infatuating for one, might be repulsive to the other.
I expect everyone to have wondered why person next to them is laughing, just as
I expect most people to have encountered love they cannot understand.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Generally, differences in taste of humour are not very much of a problem, but
when your everyday life gets permeated with shit that can only be described as
offensively boring, then there is little room for understanding. A respectful
approach is not an option when mindless attempts at amusement escape the media
and start pouring out onto the street.</p>

<p>There is no way to tell who got the charging freight train of sedative
performances going, but if there is something keeping that train speeding ahead
then it&rsquo;s the american sitcoms and worthless comedians that get too much
publicity. For me there is a crucial element in humour that is both the magic
and vigor of the performance, but it&rsquo;s a rare encounter today:</p>

<h2>Surprise</h2>

<p>The <em>unknown</em>. I need the unexpected because it pulls me out of everyday life
and lets me experience something different, something intriguing in its
peculiarity. The near total absence of surprise in most of (but in no way
limited to) the American humour, is baffling to me. How can this junk survive
(not to mention prosper)?</p>

<p>The answer lies in an entity even more baffling, the <em>viewers</em>. The survival of
these Valium substitute shows could be explained by the fact that people
actually are giving the time to enjoy this turd; there must be many of them.</p>

<p>I get annoyed by having a <em>supposed</em> comedy use jokes that you can smell from
an ocean away and then have them repeated so often that you get to experience
déjà vu every five minutes.<br/>
But these people don&rsquo;t, and they even laugh. Why?</p>

<p>Do they have a lacking comedy experience? Have they never encountered these
laughs? Do they disregard the fact that they know what is about to be said?
Could it be that they don&rsquo;t remember the gags?</p>

<p>Is chronic amnesia is the key to a more joyous life?</p>

<h2>They&rsquo;re everywhere</h2>

<p>I&rsquo;ve met these people, you have too. You might very well be one of them.
They&rsquo;re normal people that seem to live normal lives, and yet&hellip;</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not condemning you or anyone else for your taste, but I&rsquo;ve tried for too
long now to understand why people appreciate this unending stream of feces
pretending to be comedy.</p>

<p>Understanding the people around me is something I have to do every day, but
this I just can&rsquo;t grasp.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why American humour doesn't humour me]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/02/why-american-humour-doesnt-humour-me/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-02T22:11:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/02/why-american-humour-doesnt-humour-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to see Dylan Moran yesterday.<br/>
I was quite hesitant at first to order the ticket, having two exams the same
week. In retrospect however, I would never be able to forgive myself for not
taking the opportunity to see my favorite comedian, bar none.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>Me and my friend <a href="http://www.pinheadlounge.com/FreddyBoy">FreddyBoy</a> (with whom
I went to see the performance) are the type of people who have seen the
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0262150/">Black Books series</a> somewhere around
four times over, and we&rsquo;ve both lost count on how many times we&rsquo;ve seen the
standups <a href="http://youtu.be/HNAh9_BPBFk">Like, Totally</a> and <a href="http://youtu.be/lpkiIaFv5As">Monster</a> (playlist). This inevitably made us wonder whether
we would have to sit through an amalgamation of all the punchlines we knew by
heart, even though this was a part of a new tour called <a href="http://youtu.be/hieTxQ0oJPc">What it is</a> (<strong>EDIT</strong>: link added).</p>

<p>All my hesitation was gone within the first few minutes, and I was quickly
reminded why Black Books was the first TV-series that had me laughing into
pain. I spent a bit more than two hours listening to witty sarcasm and
interesting views of our everyday lives, and I just kept wanting more. The main
theme was what a person is to believe in, in this turbulent world of ours.
Science, religion and politics were discarded in favor of pleasure. Naturally,
the performance took different directions at times, which only served to make
the show more interesting.</p>

<p>Dylan Moran is a master of comedy. What puts him among the legends is the
unpredictability and his lapidary way of portraying the world around him.<br/>
The first mentioned trait is what has made me stop appreciating and literally
avoid American comedy. Often I both know every word that is going to be said,
and how it is going to be said. Indeed it might have been entertaining the
first or second time, but that&rsquo;s where it ends.</p>

<p>Brittish comedy often challenges the audience, asks it to try to keep up with
the twists and turns created by the authors. Unpredictability creates interest
because it gives us something to explore. But what if the world explored is
a bland one? That is where Moran is able to use a few select words to
exaggerate it into a caricature which grabs your attention, seemingly out of
nowhere.</p>

<p>No matter how much I love this man&rsquo;s work however, I have to point out that it
seems the ones sharing my taste are rather few. The majority of friends I&rsquo;ve
shown Moran&rsquo;s work for have sat for lengthy amounts of time wondering where the
fun is to be had. Take it as both a warning and an invitation.</p>

<p>When Moran is speaking, I listen. You should too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/05/21/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-21T16:26:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/05/21/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my new digital home.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I have contemplated the creation of this site for the longest time, but never got around doing it.
I&rsquo;m not a perfectionist by nature, but there are certain areas that I get very meticulous about, most often areas that I already know how to maneuver in, where I can have a reasonable and educated opinion. Design, while not being an expertise of any sort, is one of those areas; my page had to look and work great for me to bear with it.
Additionally, I was always bridled by the thought that my writing bore close to no relevance, interesting to me almost exclusively.</p>

<p>The first problem was solved by Squarespace (or indirectly by CO-OP, an amazing game-show that had SS as a sponsor). Not only did it help me to create a design I could feel content with, but it also gives me powerful tools to manage all aspects of the page in a simple way. This might not be a final design, nor might it be the last hosting service I&rsquo;m using, but I&rsquo;m very pleased with what I&rsquo;ve got now.</p>

<p>The second problem, while more profound, was solved swiftly over the course of a few days about half a year ago, namely when I began my scholarship at KTH.
I do believe that most of my Computer Science friends will agree when I say that we are, to a large extent, a congregation of geeks. I, for the most parts of my life, have found myself being the nerd of the pack; a nerd with the uncanny skill of being able to communicate with human beings, but nonetheless a nerd at his finest.
The things running through my head we&rsquo;re neither of others concern nor of their interest. Not the case where I&rsquo;m now.</p>

<h2>What the future holds</h2>

<p>So with a page up, and incentive to write, two questions arise: What and how?</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t predict what path this site of mine will take, but I know my current intentions. The two main sections will be the Journal and the Notes. The Notes section will be where articles, tutorials and reviews will be stored, expect tech-related work. The Journal on the other hand will be taking care of the white noise running through my head, or at least the portion that gets transcribed.
Hopefully, these two in conjunction will have me coming back to add more content. That concludes the &ldquo;What&rdquo;.</p>

<p>&ldquo;How&rdquo; is a question regarding language. My main audience will undoubtedly be Swedish, but the things I&rsquo;ll write will most likely concern an international audience, regardless of how slim it may be. Knowing that we Swedes are really good at English, I&rsquo;ve decided I&rsquo;ll start off English only. I suspect I will sooner or later add a Swedish section of some sort, but I can&rsquo;t say anything for sure.
End of beginning</p>

<p>To wrap this first post up, I want to say that my hope is that the website I&rsquo;ve created will some day be revered for the marvelous content it regularly gets updated with. One can only hope&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
