<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: personal | Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.com/blog/categories/personal/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-21T20:03:19+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why American humour doesn't humour me]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.com/blog/2009/06/02/why-american-humour-doesnt-humour-me/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-02T22:11:24+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.com/blog/2009/06/02/why-american-humour-doesnt-humour-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I went to see Dylan Moran yesterday.<br/>
I was quite hesitant at first to order the ticket, having two exams the same
week. In retrospect however, I would never be able to forgive myself for not
taking the opportunity to see my favorite comedian, bar none.</p>

<p>Me and my friend <a href="http://www.pinheadlounge.com/FreddyBoy">FreddyBoy</a> (with whom
I went to see the performance) are the type of people who have seen the
<a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0262150/">Black Books series</a> somewhere around
four times over, and we&rsquo;ve both lost count on how many times we&rsquo;ve seen the
standups <a href="http://youtu.be/HNAh9_BPBFk">Like, Totally</a> and <a href="http://youtu.be/lpkiIaFv5As">Monster</a> (playlist). This inevitably made us wonder whether
we would have to sit through an amalgamation of all the punchlines we knew by
heart, even though this was a part of a new tour called <a href="http://youtu.be/hieTxQ0oJPc">What it is</a> (link recently added).</p>

<p>All my hesitation was gone within the first few minutes, and I was quickly
reminded why Black Books was the first TV-series that had me laughing into
pain. I spent a bit more than two hours listening to witty sarcasm and
interesting views of our everyday lives, and I just kept wanting more. The main
theme was what a person is to believe in, in this turbulent world of ours.
Science, religion and politics were discarded in favor of pleasure. Naturally,
the performance took different directions at times, which only served to make
the show more interesting.</p>

<p>Dylan Moran is a master of comedy. What puts him among the legends is the
unpredictability and his lapidary way of portraying the world around him.<br/>
The first mentioned trait is what has made me stop appreciating and literally
avoid American comedy. Often I both know every word that is going to be said,
and how it is going to be said. Indeed it might have been entertaining the
first or second time, but that&rsquo;s where it ends.</p>

<p>Brittish comedy often challenges the audience, asks it to try to keep up with
the twists and turns created by the authors. Unpredictability creates interest
because it gives us something to explore. But what if the world explored is
a bland one? That is where Moran is able to use a few select words to
exaggerate it into a caricature which grabs your attention, seemingly out of
nowhere.</p>

<p>No matter how much I love this man&rsquo;s work however, I have to point out that it
seems the ones sharing my taste are rather few. The majority of friends I&rsquo;ve
shown Moran&rsquo;s work for have sat for lengthy amounts of time wondering where the
fun is to be had. Take it as both a warning and an invitation.</p>

<p>When Moran is speaking, I listen. You should too.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World!]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.com/blog/2009/05/21/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-21T16:26:52+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.com/blog/2009/05/21/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is my new digital home.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>I have contemplated the creation of this site for the longest time, but never got around doing it.
I&rsquo;m not a perfectionist by nature, but there are certain areas that I get very meticulous about, most often areas that I already know how to maneuver in, where I can have a reasonable and educated opinion. Design, while not being an expertise of any sort, is one of those areas; my page had to look and work great for me to bear with it.
Additionally, I was always bridled by the thought that my writing bore close to no relevance, interesting to me almost exclusively.</p>

<p>The first problem was solved by Squarespace (or indirectly by CO-OP, an amazing game-show that had SS as a sponsor). Not only did it help me to create a design I could feel content with, but it also gives me powerful tools to manage all aspects of the page in a simple way. This might not be a final design, nor might it be the last hosting service I&rsquo;m using, but I&rsquo;m very pleased with what I&rsquo;ve got now.</p>

<p>The second problem, while more profound, was solved swiftly over the course of a few days about half a year ago, namely when I began my scholarship at KTH.
I do believe that most of my Computer Science friends will agree when I say that we are, to a large extent, a congregation of geeks. I, for the most parts of my life, have found myself being the nerd of the pack; a nerd with the uncanny skill of being able to communicate with human beings, but nonetheless a nerd at his finest.
The things running through my head we&rsquo;re neither of others concern nor of their interest. Not the case where I&rsquo;m now.</p>

<h2>What the future holds</h2>

<p>So with a page up, and incentive to write, two questions arise: What and how?</p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t predict what path this site of mine will take, but I know my current intentions. The two main sections will be the Journal and the Notes. The Notes section will be where articles, tutorials and reviews will be stored, expect tech-related work. The Journal on the other hand will be taking care of the white noise running through my head, or at least the portion that gets transcribed.
Hopefully, these two in conjunction will have me coming back to add more content. That concludes the &ldquo;What&rdquo;.</p>

<p>&ldquo;How&rdquo; is a question regarding language. My main audience will undoubtedly be Swedish, but the things I&rsquo;ll write will most likely concern an international audience, regardless of how slim it may be. Knowing that we Swedes are really good at English, I&rsquo;ve decided I&rsquo;ll start off English only. I suspect I will sooner or later add a Swedish section of some sort, but I can&rsquo;t say anything for sure.
End of beginning</p>

<p>To wrap this first post up, I want to say that my hope is that the website I&rsquo;ve created will some day be revered for the marvelous content it regularly gets updated with. One can only hope&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
