<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tech | Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/categories/tech/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T17:29:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Vim plugins - Why]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/04/13/vim-plugins-why/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-13T23:12:33+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2013/04/13/vim-plugins-why</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A lot of times when I meet &ldquo;Vim neophytes&rdquo; they mention that Vim is a great
editor, but they miss certain features that they find in their previous
editor/IDE of choice. Often this will be a case of them not having learnt the
Vim way of doing the same task, but occasionally you&rsquo;ll have to tell them that
&ldquo;Vim doesn&rsquo;t do that&rdquo;.<br/>
Indeed, these days if you don&rsquo;t want to hop between different applications (all
of them having the primary purpose of editing text of some kind) you&rsquo;ll want
features that go beyond &ldquo;editing text&rdquo;.</p>

<h4>These days an editor can&rsquo;t just be an editor.</h4>

<!--more-->


<p>I&rsquo;ve met programmers who say that they&rsquo;re fine with using Eclipse for Java, Vim
for Ruby and then nano for minor edits in configuration files. Any workflow like
this makes no sense to me, since I wouldn&rsquo;t want to edit text in anything that
isn&rsquo;t Vim. Most people don&rsquo;t see how it could be any different&hellip;</p>

<p>&hellip;until you show them the wealth of plugins available.</p>

<h2>How to get them installed</h2>

<p>The classic way of installing plugins is to get the latest version from
<a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/index.php">vim.org&rsquo;s scripts</a> page in the form of an
archive and just extract the contents into <code>~/.vim/</code>.</p>

<p>Now that you know about how it was done once upon a time, please refrain from
ever using this method (unless you want a spectacular mess inside your
Vim-directory).</p>

<p>These days people have plugins in separate directories, all of them stored in
some central plugin directory (most often <code>~/vim/bundle</code>). These plugin
directories are in turn loaded by some &ldquo;plugin handler&rdquo;, of which there are
many.</p>

<p>A lengthy list of handlers <a href="http://vim-scripts.org/vim/tools.html">can be found here</a>. It doesn&rsquo;t matter that much which one
you choose, but it might be a good idea to go with one of the more popular ones,
which are Pathogen, Vundle and VAM (vim-addon-manager).</p>

<h2>My setup</h2>

<p>I prefer to do the handling and updating of plugins outside of Vim, so I&rsquo;ve got
the following setup:</p>

<p>I&rsquo;ve got a &ldquo;dotfiles&rdquo; git-repository to which I&rsquo;ve added my Vim-plugins as
submodules. This allows me to update all my plugins (along with any other
git-repos I&rsquo;ve added as dotfiles) with one command (alias it to something
shorter):</p>

<pre><code>git submodule foreach git pull origin master
</code></pre>

<p>Committing these updated plugins with <code>git commit -a</code> and pushing the dotfiles
repo will then allow me to clone the repo anywhere and get all my plugins at the
same time (just make sure to clone with the <code>--recursive</code> flag).</p>

<p>Standing in <code>~</code>, adding the plugins would be done with a command like this:</p>

<pre><code>git submodule add git://github.com/linduxed/vim-linduxed-theme.git .vim/bundle/vim-linduxed-theme
</code></pre>

<p>I then use Pathogen to load all the plugins (read its FAQ about adding it as
a submodule, if that interests you).</p>

<p>I should also mention that while not necessary, structuring up your <code>~/.vimrc</code>
somewhat could be of great help, since it will increase in size after you start
adding plugins. <code>:set foldmethod=marker</code> and <a href="https://github.com/linduxed/dotfiles/blob/master/.vimrc">adding some markers</a> helps a lot.</p>

<p>If you don&rsquo;t already have a <code>.vimrc</code>, this is a <a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-sensible">good starting point</a>.</p>

<h2>Which plugins do I get?</h2>

<p>There are quite a few plugins out there, so I&rsquo;ll just get you started with those
that I find most significantly improve my Vim experience. Click on the plugin
names to be taken to their respective repositories.</p>

<p>If you&rsquo;re hungry for more after going through this list, check out
<a href="https://github.com/linduxed/dotfiles/tree/master/.vim/bundle">the other plugins I&rsquo;ve got in my setup</a> and go to
<a href="http://vim-scripts.org/">Vim Scripts</a> or <a href="http://www.vim.org/scripts/index.php">the official script page</a>.</p>

<h3>File and buffer navigation</h3>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/kien/ctrlp.vim/">CTRLP</a></h4>

<p>There are a few fuzzy-search plugins out there, the most well known ones being
<a href="https://github.com/wincent/Command-T">Command-T</a>, <a href="https://bitbucket.org/ns9tks/vim-fuzzyfinder/">FuzzyFinder</a> and CTRLP. While they&rsquo;re all
pretty similar when it comes to finding files, I like CTRLP a bit more because
it lets you fuzzy find among buffers and most-recently-used files as well.</p>

<p>As long as you know the name of the file you&rsquo;re looking for, this type of plugin
takes care of most file opening operations, due to it being so quick.</p>

<p>In case you haven&rsquo;t seen fuzzy-finders before, here&rsquo;s a quick demonstration. This is what it looks like when I look for <code>game/ai/ai_dropnodes.c</code> in the <a href="http://www.warsow.net/">Warsow</a> source code:</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog/ctrlp.gif' width='' height='' title='CTRLP in action. Looking for <code>ai_dropnodes.c</code>.'><span class='caption-text'>CTRLP in action. Looking for <code>ai_dropnodes.c</code>.</span></span></p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/sandeepcr529/Buffet.vim">buffet</a></h4>

<p>There&rsquo;s a lot of overlap between CTRLP&rsquo;s buffer switching functionality and the
functionality of buffet, but if you want a tool that does nothing but switch
between buffers swiftly, this plugin is probably it.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/nerdtree.git">nerdtree</a></h4>

<p>While I&rsquo;m using it less and less due to CTRLP, nerdtree is still the easiest way
to explore your filesystem without exiting Vim.</p>

<h3>Code writing helpers</h3>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/Lokaltog/vim-easymotion.git">vim-easymotion</a></h4>

<p>The big one. This plugin changed the way I move around in code completely. While
Vim gives you a great set of tools to move around in code (one of the things
that take the longest to master), this plugin takes it to another level. It&rsquo;s
probably the closest thing to mouse cursor accuracy you can get, while not
wasting time to fetch the mouse itself.</p>

<p>Words don&rsquo;t do this justice, so here&rsquo;s a video:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Dmv6-dguS3g" width="605" height="360" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-surround">vim-surround</a></h4>

<p>Makes the task of surrounding text with quotes, parentheses, brackets, etc. much
easier. Also provides quick removal and changing of surrounding characters.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/garbas/vim-snipmate.git">vim-snipmate</a></h4>

<p>If you haven&rsquo;t used an editor with snippets before, it&rsquo;s basically a set of
templates, small pieces of code which are often used in which you fill out the
relevant fields.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/xV2IsE5OHd4" width="605" height="360" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></p>

<p>I should mention that at the time of writing the linked project has its
development slowed down, with another project called <a href="https://github.com/SirVer/ultisnips">UltiSnips</a> getting a lot of traction (along with
a <a href="https://github.com/MarcWeber/ultisnips/">fork</a> made by an ex-snipmate
developer).</p>

<p>The situation is a bit complicated, but at the moment snipmate works fine for me
so I don&rsquo;t see a reason to switch.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/nerdcommenter.git">nerdcommenter</a></h4>

<p>Indispensable plugin that makes the creation and handling of comments in code
a breeze.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/jiangmiao/auto-pairs">auto-pairs</a></h4>

<p>Inserts a closing parenthesis, bracket, curly brace or quote when you insert an
opening one. Also knows what to do with braces if you press enter inside them
(indentation and new empty line between them) along with some other nice things.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s also <a href="https://github.com/Townk/vim-autoclose">AutoClose</a> which does
pretty much the same thing.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/godlygeek/tabular.git">tabular</a></h4>

<p>For the people who like their code pretty (I obsess over that kind of stuff)
this plugin aligns code.</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog/tabular.gif' width='' height='' title='Tabular lining stuff up.'><span class='caption-text'>Tabular lining stuff up.</span></span></p>

<h3>Miscellaneous</h3>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/linduxed/vim-linduxed-theme.git">vim-linduxed-theme</a></h4>

<p>This is here for two reasons:</p>

<ol>
<li>Plugging your own stuff is always nice.</li>
<li>People should get any theme.</li>
</ol>


<p>Seriously, the stock themes aren&rsquo;t that pretty and the ones you can find on the
internet are both varied and beautiful (not to mention that some have more
detailed syntax highlighting).</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s a list of repos to look through (there are many others):</p>

<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-vividchalk">Vividchalk</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/daylerees/colour-schemes">Dayle Rees' color scheme collection</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/altercation/solarized">Solarized</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/chriskempson/tomorrow-theme">Tomorrow</a></li>
</ul>


<h4><a href="https://github.com/sjl/gundo.vim.git">gundo.vim</a></h4>

<p>Many people aren&rsquo;t even aware of the fact that Vim has a branching undo history,
but this plugin makes it accessible. It upgrades the undo-tree from &ldquo;never use
it&rdquo; to &ldquo;use it all the time&rdquo;.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-fugitive">vim-fugitive</a></h4>

<p><blockquote><p>I&rsquo;m not going to lie to you; fugitive.vim may very well be the best Git wrapper of all time.</p><footer><strong>Tim Pope</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I&rsquo;ll have to agree. The extensive functionality is covered in detailed by Drew
Neil in his Vimcasts videos, starting at <a href="http://vimcasts.org/episodes/fugitive-vim---a-complement-to-command-line-git/">episode #31</a>.</p>

<p>If I was to pick just one of the many great features this plugin provides, then
it&rsquo;s the ability to open up the index version of the files and edit that while
having the version from the working directory open. This is like a superior
version of <code>git add --patch</code>, which is reason enough to get this.</p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/scrooloose/syntastic">syntastic</a></h4>

<p>This plugin runs your code through a linter or syntax checker upon every save
and loads the warnings/errors into the location list and displays markers in the
gutter to indicate on what rows the warnings/errors are.</p>

<p>Incredibly helpful, you wouldn&rsquo;t know how much until you&rsquo;ve tried it. Syntastic
has code ready for the major linters/checkers/compilers for most languages.</p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s me fixing some warnings that pylint gives about &ldquo;no space after comma&rdquo;
(pylint warns about non-compliance with <a href="http://www.python.org/dev/peps/pep-0008/">PEP8</a>):</p>

<p><span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/blog/syntastic.gif' width='' height='' title='Syntastic giving warnings with the help of pylint.'><span class='caption-text'>Syntastic giving warnings with the help of pylint.</span></span></p>

<h4><a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-unimpaired">vim-unimpaired</a></h4>

<p>Gives you a set of very useful bindings.</p>

<h2>Only the beginning</h2>

<p>The big category of plugins that I&rsquo;ve omitted is language/framework specific
plugins. I&rsquo;ve got a lot of those, but each specific one might not be useful to
everyone. With that said, there are some language specific plugins that are
really powerful and should most definitely be used if they align with what
you&rsquo;re coding in (<a href="https://github.com/tpope/vim-rails"><code>rails.vim</code> by Tim Pope</a>
is, from what I&rsquo;ve heard, considered to be a major source of Vim converts from
TextMate).</p>

<p>Once you start customizing your Vim, you&rsquo;ll notice that there are many areas
which you can improve with a plugin here and there. Just remember to stop and
consider if the functionality you&rsquo;re looking for isn&rsquo;t already available in
stock Vim.</p>

<p>As mentioned before, if you need some inspiration you can check out
<a href="https://github.com/linduxed/dotfiles/tree/master/.vim/bundle">the plugins I use</a> and if you&rsquo;ve got
any problems, just fire up your IRC client of choice and head over to
<code>#vim@freenode.org</code>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Not ready for the switch]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/05/10/not-ready-for-the-switch/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-10T14:12:25+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/05/10/not-ready-for-the-switch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, for some unknown reason, <a href="http://5digits.org/pentadactyl/">Pentadactyl</a> decided that it didn&rsquo;t want to work any more.
I still have no idea why, and since I&rsquo;ve been suspending my computer for quite
a few days now, it might actually have to do with me upgrading Firefox from 11
to 12 quite recently. The problem was actually pretty easily solved by
downloading the latest nightly and just fire that up, but before I did that, the
sudden loss of Vim-style navigation inspired me to pick up an old project of
mine:</p>

<p>Moving from Firefox to uzbl.</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>It sounds so beautiful</h2>

<p>For those who don&rsquo;t know what <a href="http://www.uzbl.org/">uzbl</a> is, it&rsquo;s basically
a browser that adheres to the UNIX philosophy of &ldquo;doing one thing and doing it
well&rdquo;. What that means is that the browser is split up into small pieces; you
have <code>uzbl-core</code> which is not much more than Webkit with some interfaces on top
of it, and the actual thing that resembles a browser is either <code>uzbl-browser</code> or
<code>uzbl-tabbed</code>.<br/>
You know you&rsquo;re in for a ride if the developers initially didn&rsquo;t have
<code>uzbl-tabbed</code> at all since &ldquo;window managers should be handling the different
instances of the browser, not the browser itself&rdquo;. All the basic functionality
that one takes for granted in other browsers that aren&rsquo;t strictly browsing are
extras here; bookmarks, downloading, completion and other functionality that you
come to expect are scripts that are loaded by the main configuration file.</p>

<h2>But the beauty comes at a price</h2>

<p>If the application is nice then I&rsquo;m willing to put the time into configuring it.
Whether it&rsquo;s my ZSH terminal, Vim, Firefox or something else, I&rsquo;ll put in the
work to get it <em>just right</em> if I know that I can get that magnificent end result
that I envision. uzbl sounds fantastic because I like the notion of being able
to configure a system from the ground up, to see what happens and to know what
does what.</p>

<p>There&rsquo;s just one big problem however:</p>

<p>The work necessary to get uzbl to the state my Firefox is in with the numerous
extensions and custom configurations would take <em>ages</em>, if at all possible.
I decided that I can try to live without NoScript, BetterPrivacy, Firebug and
some other nice extensions, as long as I get what I consider to be core
functionality to work smoothly. Even this (what I would consider modest)
aspiration is a challenge to say the least.</p>

<p>The default configuration gives you Vim-like control, with hjkl-movement and
some other things that you might recognize if you&rsquo;re coming from
Pentadactyl/Vimperator, but the similarities end fairly quickly. Once the basic
keys were reconfigured to my liking, one of the first things I wanted to tweak
was that since I use <code>uzbl_tabbed</code>, I&rsquo;ll want to reconfigure the <code>NEW_WINDOW</code>
action to load links in new tabs. The fact that only the action <code>NEW_TAB</code> worked
and not the other two potentially nice ones (<code>NEW_BG_TAB</code> and <code>NEW_BG_TAB_NEXT</code>)
was a shame, doubly so when there&rsquo;s no information for how get it to work.</p>

<h2>You&rsquo;re on your own</h2>

<p>This was the first encounter (out of many, I might add) with what eventually led
me to give up on the browser. There&rsquo;s no comprehensive source of information
about uzbl… anywhere.</p>

<p>I use Archlinux on my main computer but I know that I might not have been if it
wasn&rsquo;t for the fantastic Wiki. I don&rsquo;t know if that huge source of information
has spoiled me, but I feel like I&rsquo;m done with the days of guessing myself forth
when configuring software. I don&rsquo;t enjoy being in the situation of “Well I&rsquo;d
really like to do foobar, so I guess I&rsquo;ll scour tens of config files to see if
someone has done something remotely similar from which I can extrapolate some
kind of solution”.</p>

<p><em>I&rsquo;m done with that shit.</em></p>

<p>The Arch Wiki proves that even if you put docstrings for every line in your
configuration, a Wiki page with some quick and helpful tweaks that every new
user would make, is a thousand times better. As soon as I got any idea on how
I&rsquo;d like to tweak the interface of uzbl, it was followed by the realization that
there&rsquo;s neither a quick nor an obvious way to do it.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.uzbl.org/wiki/">official Wiki</a> is so barren that it seems to be
made by and exclusively for the current/future developers. Google isn&rsquo;t much
more helpful, the usual searches for HOWTOs or tutorials yield not much more
information than what one would derive from the sample configs that one can find
in the Wiki.</p>

<h2>See you some other time</h2>

<p>The impression I get is that if you&rsquo;re not ready to figure it out, then you
shouldn&rsquo;t even start. I gave it quite a few hours and at a certain point decided
that fixing Pentadactyl would be far more beneficial and far less time
consuming.</p>

<p>Some day I&rsquo;ll probably give it another shot, but by that time I&rsquo;ll probably come
prepared with far more patience and without the expectation to actually replace
Firefox.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[When the tools just don't work]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/03/15/when-the-tools-just-dont-work/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T12:38:30+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/03/15/when-the-tools-just-dont-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a while you stumble on that area of software that Linux just
doesn&rsquo;t have covered. You might now be thinking that I&rsquo;d like to talk about
audio and video editing. A fair guess, since you&rsquo;ll hear people talk about
these two as areas where the other platforms have significantly more
sophisticated software available. But this isn&rsquo;t what I&rsquo;m going to talk about.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>You see, I&rsquo;ve had a look at the video and audio editors out there for Linux, and
while it&rsquo;s generally not as good as what you&rsquo;d have on OSX or Windows, there are
projects that make honest efforts to compete (Rosegarden comes to mind). I think
even the cynics can at least call the tools in these areas “rudimentary”.</p>

<p>“Streaming your desktop” in Linux, however, is one area you can&rsquo;t even fucking
call rudimentary. The appropriate description I&rsquo;ve come up with is “technically
working with the help of wizardry”, and I&rsquo;m thinking about whether that&rsquo;s too
generous.</p>

<h2>No audience</h2>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say I&rsquo;m particularly surprised by this situation, because apart from the
occasional recorded screen cast for some brand new package, there isn&rsquo;t that
much of a need, it seems. We don&rsquo;t have the games to stream, which I would
assume is a large part of what drives the revenue of a page like Justin.tv.</p>

<p>I assume most of the people who code in Linux aren&rsquo;t exactly eager to stream and
narrate their work, which could have been that “other area” of content that
would have driven the development of tools for streaming. I understand that the
Linux community might have less scenarios under which one would want to stream
one&rsquo;s desktop, but I&rsquo;m still surprised by how dire the software situation is.</p>

<h2>The tools</h2>

<p>From what I&rsquo;ve gathered, the most “mature” application available for handling
the various aspects of streaming (sound, picture, overlays and so on) is
WebcamStudio, which didn&rsquo;t exactly work. At the best of times it was giving me
something that looked like the stream I wanted to pass on, but I never managed
to actually get any streaming site to accept the data. This completely sidesteps
the issue that is the buggy-as-fuck interface, that neither looks good nor works
well.</p>

<p>The most stable solution I&rsquo;ve found, that has actually let me see my desktop on
the internet, is the combination of:</p>

<ul>
<li>Letting VLC capture your desktop with a wide array of flags to make sure it
comes out right. Figuring out those was a ton of fun.</li>
<li>Having a script called “jtvlc” catch the data and send it in through the
Justin.tv API.</li>
</ul>


<p>It&rsquo;s way better than nothing, but this gives me absolutely no ability to
customize the output, except choosing what part of my monitor set-up it should
grab.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>In a way, I hope I&rsquo;ve missed something; I hope there&rsquo;s an obscure package that
simply grabs the part of the desktop you want, has a nice interface, and just
works. If that magic package exists however, then I haven&rsquo;t found it.</p>

<p>There are times when I really would have liked to share the view of one of my
screens, with some embedded microphone commentary. When the ideas pop up, I&rsquo;d
like to go ahead and just try them out, but in this case, I&rsquo;m completely
hindered. It might be that the process of getting these things to work under the
other systems is also a chore, but at least I&rsquo;ve seen plenty examples of there
being an end result. That&rsquo;s something I&rsquo;ve yet to see here in Linux.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Code I enjoy]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/02/27/code-i-enjoy/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-27T18:59:41+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2012/02/27/code-i-enjoy</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Being a CS student means that I will be forced to code in a variety of
languages. A lot of our code will be written in Java or C++, but we&rsquo;ll
necessarily get in touch with many other languages, spanning over multiple
paradigms.</p>

<p>By no means am I a good programmer yet, but the exposure to the different ways
of crafting code has led me to think about what I value (as a novice
programmer) in a language. It&rsquo;s, after all, my main tool of expression.<br/>
Is it the brevity of the code? What the community surrounding the language is
like? Paradigm or strong vs. weak typing? Or could it be that I need the
language to be as “simple” as possible for me to be able to formulate ideas?</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>My roots, or the lack of them</h2>

<p>My first language I got to code in was actually Borland Delphi. I didn&rsquo;t really
know what I was doing, I just followed a guide that let me create a “guess what
number I&rsquo;m thinking of”-application with a GUI that I got to draw. I was
probably about ten years old at that time, and it wasn&rsquo;t until late elementary
that I got acquainted with Java, in a programming course.</p>

<p>Since a bit of Delphi was all I had under my belt at the time, Java was quite
the challenge at first. I didn&rsquo;t like the notion of there being things that
I had to write that I didn&rsquo;t fully understand the purpose of (the concept of
“static” was a prime example). Also, while I understood the necessity of
getters and setters, it felt weird that I had to write them everywhere;
I already had something against boilerplate.</p>

<p>Java has been with me for more than a decade, so I&rsquo;ve gotten used to its
intricacies, but it wasn&rsquo;t the language that got me really interested in
programming.</p>

<h2>Inspiration and motivation</h2>

<p>While I tried borrowing introductory books for both Java and C++, neither of
the languages really interested me. I felt that there was so much to learn,
just to accomplish the simplest of things. That&rsquo;s when a friend of mine
introduced me to Python.</p>

<p>The thing I immediately liked about Python was the brevity. To this day I find
that there&rsquo;s something special about seeing text no longer than a screen full
(very reminiscent of pseudo code, one might add) execute and work its magic.
It&rsquo;s empowering in a way, to so easily make so much happen. To let ideas
transform into code at such a quick rate becomes not only a tool, but
a motivation; when scraping together an application gets easier, the
imagination takes over.</p>

<p>Another thing that I hadn&rsquo;t experienced up until my encounter with Python was
easily readable code. I didn&rsquo;t know of the expression at that time, but
“self-documenting code” was something I really enjoyed; whether the names got
longer or the code had to be restructured, it was worth it for the readability.</p>

<p>Today it so happens that I code more Ruby than I do Python, but I still love
the language. Python both motivated and influenced me, but not to the extent
that Haskell did.</p>

<h2>A different way of doing things</h2>

<p>Haskell is special to me because it showed me a totally different way of
crafting code while still keeping it short and expressive. Once I got past the
peculiarity of functional programming it made me re-evaluate what I&rsquo;d consider
“comfortable” when I write code.</p>

<p>As soon as I got the taste for higher order functions, currying, lazy
evaluation and all of the other facilities that Haskell offers, I started to
think about why other languages hadn&rsquo;t introduced me to these concepts.</p>

<p>The thing I love the most about the language is that solving problems in it is
a satisfying experience. When the recursive thinking became more natural, and
I devoted the time to expand my vocabulary of functions that Haskell offered,
magic happened. A friend jokingly referred to Haskell as a “set of glorified
one-liners”, and while there&rsquo;s more to it than that, there&rsquo;s joy in crafting
those one-liners.</p>

<h2>Learning one&rsquo;s preferences</h2>

<p><blockquote><p>A language that doesn&rsquo;t affect the way you think about programming, is not worth knowing.</p><footer><strong>Alan J. Perlis</strong> <cite>Epigrams on Programming</cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I can&rsquo;t say that I had the greatest time during my struggles with Prolog, or
that fighting with all the details one has to keep in his head when writing
Assembly was a pleasure, but it made me see things differently.</p>

<p>I guess it&rsquo;s a “coming of age” thing for a programmer to realize not what you
want to code, but how you want to do it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
