<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: politics | Rants of a geek]]></title>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-22T17:29:32+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://linduxed.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[linduxed]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The black sheep of social media]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/09/28/the-black-sheep-of-social-media/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-28T00:16:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/09/28/the-black-sheep-of-social-media</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week the company had a group activity where the following question had to
be answered:</p>

<h4>&ldquo;How can we make our company seen?&rdquo;</h4>

<p>A broad but familiar question, one that I assume most companies try to figure
out the answer to.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>At first I thought that the sandwich buffet would be the main attraction of the
evening; I might have some qualities of a marketer, but my days in
telemarketing weren&rsquo;t the most joyful I&rsquo;ve had.<br/>
Most groups employed the classical way making a company known, that is to
plaster our logo on everything that can fit it. There were some interesting
ideas like offering WiFi hotspots at the conventions that the company tends to
attend, but in general a flurry of company car stickers, usb keys and coffee
cups were suggested.</p>

<p>I had the good fortune however of sitting next to a table where the idea of
a Twitter account emerged. This would be a channel outwards for the company the
table thought, a news feed. The idea sounded interesting until it occurred to
me that these people had no broader intentions than dropping a release
announcement at times in less than 140 characters; it turned out that I (and
a lone co-worker that shared my views) had to mention that moving into social
networking implies that there has to be something social about the new way of
communicating. We already have a web page for announcements.</p>

<h2>Learn from others</h2>

<p>The last time I witnessed a remarkable failure in trying to penetrate the
social media, with the one responsible never having tried to do so before, was
during the EU-elections in Sweden.<br/>
The seven established parties noticed that the digital campaign for Obama was
highly successful, and therefore decided that bombarding YouTube, Facebook,
Twitter and so on with sponsored content would grant them instant victory.</p>

<p>What neither they then nor my company now realized was that to be of relevance
you have to be someone, and by someone I mean an entity that generates
a two-way discussion.</p>

<p>The &ldquo;two-way&rdquo; part is where the secret lies. The only party that had
a substancial and lasting presence during the elections was, unsurprisingly,
the Pirate Party. What they did was to start heated debates on blogs, comment
sections and on Twitter feeds. People sharing their points of view and
defending them vigorously because of a passion for the issues at hand.</p>

<p>People. Opinions. <em>Passion</em>.</p>

<p>Indications of a driving force that can generate interest, those are the things
that will make you want to make contact and possibly spread the three above
further.</p>

<h2>How to be seen</h2>

<p>So the Twitter feed was a great idea for the company, but it does take that
lively person to keep it going. My suggestion was at the time was to appoint
a person who has a fairly good insight into most parts of the company to on
a routinely basis scurry around the web for places to make our voice heard on.<br/>
It doesn&rsquo;t matter whether it would be writing a column on some page related to
our area of expertise, or if it would be posting a tiny tweet to compliment the
author of an article regarding a hot topic. Turn the digital avatar of our
company into a presence.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not a master of this subject, but wouldn&rsquo;t it be nice if it more often felt
like the one selling you something is someone you&rsquo;d like to recommend to your
friend?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[At the snap of your fingers]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/20/at-the-snap-of-your-fingers/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-20T18:23:15+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/20/at-the-snap-of-your-fingers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m by now profoundly tired of the misconception that has been floating around
in our modern digitalized society for too long of a time. It thrives within the
older generations, but is in no way limited to them. It goes like this:</p>

<h4>Piracy is theft!</h4>

<p>Stop. <strong>Now</strong>.</p>

<!--more-->


<p>This statement not only indicates a lack of understanding of how the digital
world works, but quite often also a lack of <em>will</em> to understand it, the latter
being a really frightening aversion to future.</p>

<p>Most often the idea of a lost profit is the fundament of this flawed thinking,
and the subsequent assumption of criminality doesn&rsquo;t make the train of thought
better tied to reality in any way.<br/>
What it is tied to however is an age-old view of how the immaterial is spread,
a view that is not compatible with the internet; internet is not like anything
humanity has every experienced before.</p>

<p>In May 2009 at TED, Clay Shirkey had a talk called
<a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/clay_shirky_how_cellphones_twitter_facebook_can_make_history.html">&ldquo;How cell phones, Twitter, Facebook can make history&rdquo;</a>,
and while I urge all my visitors to see this talk (as well as his other one),
there is one important quote that sums it up quite well:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The internet is the first medium in history that has native support for groups<br/>and conversation at the same time.</p></p><p><p>Whereas the phones gave us the one-to-one pattern, and television, radio,<br/>magazines and books gave us the one-to-many pattern, the internet gave us the<br/>many-to-many pattern.</p></p><p><p>For the first time media is natively good at supporting these kinds of conversations.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>A keyword in this talk is revolution. It is a strong word, but an accurate one
nonetheless. When a large amount of people are given the power to create,
recieve and share intellectual content at will and in unrestricted amounts,
then there is no other word that will describe the phenomenon better.<br/>
So the fundament of the fallacy is the notion that the internet fits within the
old boundries of the centralised systems, the corporate control and the old
media. It does not.</p>

<h2>An alternate reality</h2>

<p>Another issue with the mentioned &ldquo;lost profit&rdquo;-explanation of why digital
piracy should be considered a criminal act is that this way of thinking is
completely incompatible with the idea of altruistic sharing. Within most
cultures around the world, sharing items of your ownership is considered an act
of friendship, especially if done voluntarily.</p>

<p>Now I hear the opposition wildly shouting &ldquo;Not at the cost of someone else!&rdquo;.
The thing is however that when saying such a thing the opposition expects to
get money for things they have no control over. Another important question is
whether they have the right to have control over them. When a piece of
information is digitalized the idea of the opposition is that there is a fee
that should carry with the very existence of the work.</p>

<p>Let me present you with a hypothetical alternate reality:<br/>
Imagine there was a fairly unknown, but very easy way to replicate matter;
cross your fingers on the left hand, look at the object you want more of, snap
the fingers of the right hand and suddenly you&rsquo;ve got more!</p>

<p>This knowledge was at first limited to a few select people called &ldquo;geeks&rdquo;, but
because it was so easy to do, soon the world&rsquo;s populace was perfectly aware
that if anyone wanted something then a snap of your fingers was all you needed.</p>

<p>Let&rsquo;s say you&rsquo;re out with your friends some evening in this world. You all went
to an event of some sort, had a good time, and sooner or later found that it
was time to return home. The problem was however that you had some urgent
matter to take care of, making you drive in a completely opposite direction,
which of course conflicted with the plans of your friends.<br/>
An idea stroke. At the snap of your fingers your friends could have a car each.
<strong>A snap</strong>.</p>

<p>What should one do? Help your friends at no cost whatsoever? Refuse?<br/>
At what grounds would you refuse? That they should buy one themselves when
you&rsquo;ve got a thousand in your fingertips? And why would the thought even cross
your mind? These are your friends in need, and with an infinite amount of cars
at your disposal it would seem odd not to help them out.</p>

<h2>Your turn to think</h2>

<p>This is quite a ways from our world, but the observant have already noted that
this is how the digital world has always worked. If an item is infinite in
amount (which is a tad more than what the old generation is used to) then one
must question whether to control this item is feasible, reasonable and most
importantly righteous.</p>

<p>The digital world is here to stay, I wonder how long it will take for some to
adjust to that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pirate Party gets into EU-parliament]]></title>
    <link href="http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/09/pirate-party-gets-into-eu-parliament/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-09T18:35:27+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://linduxed.github.io/blog/2009/06/09/pirate-party-gets-into-eu-parliament</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve for some time now looked at extreme sides in conflicts/discussions as
a kind of a necessity. It&rsquo;s not that you will always agree with them, but they
will inevitably broaden the scope of the argument.<br/>
I might, for instance, not agree with right-wing extremists, but having them
there forces one into debates that would otherwise never be had, opening ones
eyes to opinions outside what is seen as &ldquo;normal&rdquo;.</p>

<p>It was this kind of blindness to other opinion that permeated the Swedish
(although not in any way limited to) politics when it came to a certain
subject:</p>

<!--more-->


<h2>Digital Integrity</h2>

<p>For the longest time, internet as an entity has been completely outside of the
scope of Swedish politics. Media uses it extensively, the companies love it and
the people wouldn&rsquo;t want to live without it.</p>

<p>The current generation of politicians however have other issues to deal with,
be it the climate, the unstable economy or health care. In no way are these
subjects unimportant, they&rsquo;re crucial to the workings of the society and should
not be neglected.<br/>
These are however problems that have been around for a great deal of time, and
both the people and the politicians seem to have fallen into a jog trot where
the same range of problems are debated year in and year out, with the same
arguments coming from the same parties.</p>

<p>Internet does not fit into that jog trot; internet is an anarchistic yet
beautifully democratic place that collectively runs circles around any other
medium out there, a completely new way of thinking. The people have been given
an network that enables them to gain and share information, culture and tools
at will. A hive mind has been created.<br/>
However, a power of this magnitude can be used for a variety of different
things, and some found that variety dangerous.</p>

<p>&ldquo;In service of the industries&rdquo; the state has given internet users a rough
treatment the recent years, mainly (but not limited to) laws crafted by the
hands of lobbyists. The politicians should most definitely seek for help if
they know nothing on the subject, but asking profit driven organizations for
advice has so far only resulted in everything from the mild offenses to the
draconian and deeply disturbing laws.</p>

<p>It gets even worse when the words &ldquo;For the public safety.&rdquo; are used.
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FRA_law">Spying actively on millions of innocent people</a>, forcing companies to
<a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Telecommunications_data_retention#Data_retention_in_the_European_Union">store every last bit of digital information for at least six months</a>
and turning <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-Counterfeiting_Trade_Agreement">customs personnel into arbitrary copyright enforcers</a> are some of
my favourite material for getting my rant mode on.</p>

<h2>The movement</h2>

<p>The 7th of June here in Sweden it became apparent that there were those that
didn&rsquo;t find this comforting at all. On the evening of election day, having
counted a large percentage of the districts, the Pirate Party had gotten 7,1%
of the votes (at the moment of writing 7,31%).<br/>
I&rsquo;m not saying that each and every one of those votes came from the intelligent
and rational people who want to preserve the rights to a protected digital
life, I wouldn&rsquo;t be surprised if there were some who solely voted on the basis
of wanting to preserve their ability to get hold of expensive digital material
for free. On the other hand, there is a whole cast of people who vote for the
social democrats only because they know that with them in power they can count
on more welfare payments (which is one of the main reasons the Swedish economy
was in tatters before the last elections.<br/>
So there are always those who will vote for what some will say are the &ldquo;wrong&rdquo;
reasons, but isn&rsquo;t that what democracy is about?</p>

<p>I am quite pleased to say that I was one of those who voted the party forth.
Last elections to the Swedish parliament I voted for the moderates, mainly
because I found, and still find, them the only party that has a clue how to
handle the economy. The fact that they also support nuclear power and got all
the welfare exploiters back into work has me overjoyed. But when it comes to
the integrity and internet issues I feel the Alliance (as the right oriented
government coalition is called) has totally dropped the ball.</p>

<h2>Why the party is needed</h2>

<p>A blogger recently <a href="http://kozue.wordpress.com/2009/05/22/blablabla-enfrageparti-blablabla/">wrote a response</a> to
a columnist from Swedish Metro who found the
<a href="http://www.dalademokraten.se/Templates/pages/news.aspx?id=70158&amp;epslanguage=sv">Pirate Party and the concept of single-issue parties repulsive</a>
(Swedish), an element that makes democracy more stupid than it should be.
A translation of the reply follows:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>You get into your house and take off your shoes. You take out a piece of paper<br/>to make a to-do list. Time to get one&rsquo;s hands dirty!</p></p><p><p>You walk through the apartment and take notes of everything needed to be done.<br/>There&rsquo;s a buildup of ice in the freezer, the doorknob to the bathroom is a bit<br/>loose, the oven could use some cleaning, it&rsquo;s dusty behind the computer desk,<br/>the laundry basket is broken, the wooden chairs on the balcony need to get<br/>oiled up, the coffee-table has gotten some specks of candle-grease on it, the<br/>TV is on fire, the bathroom mirror has some stains on it, the toilet paper has<br/>almost run out, some bottles are to taken to the recycling station, some<br/>accounts are to be done, a light bulb has gone out in the bedroom, a blind is<br/>broken and the entrance hall really needs a repainting of the walls.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>So in the words of the blogger, all we pirates want is really to get in, put
out the fire, and then let the guy fix the rest as he pleases. We know that
this guy and his friends have painted entrance halls and cleaned coffee-tables
a thousand times over and we trust he won&rsquo;t do anything extraordinarily stupid
this time over, but if putting the fire out is not his top priority then at
least let us do it.</p>

<h2>A black flag waves</h2>

<p>I think this is nothing but a start. In every file sharer there is a potential
voter for the Pirate Party. In every person who is against American lobbies
poisoning global politics, there is a potential voter for the Pirate Party. In
everyone who finds total surveillance of the digital realm a scary thought,
there is a potential voter for the Pirate Party.</p>

<p>I voted for them now, and I hope that Christian Engström and possibly
(depending on whether she gets into the EU-parliament) Amelia Andersdotter
serve as a different perspective in EU, as the extremists that broaden the
scope.</p>

<p>One can at least have hope.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
